Since 2003, a special type of scam targeting the elderly
Od roku 2003 w Japonii króluje biorące na cel osoby starsze
called the money transfer scam has proliferated in Japan.
oszustwo zwane „przekrętem na przelew”.
Financial damages increased every year, reaching 56.5 billion yen in 2014.
Straty finansowe rosną z roku na rok. W 2014 r. wynosiły 56,5 miliarda jenów.
Now, in 2019, scammers have changed their techniques,
W 2019 roku oszuści zmienili metody,
and the damage continues.
w dalszym ciągu okradając obywateli.
CHIBA PREFECTURAL POLICE
POLICJA PREFEKTURY CHIBA
Stop!
Nie!
Let go of me!
Puśćcie mnie!
You're alive.
Ty żyjesz.
I don't die easily.
Ciężko mnie zabić.
EPISODE 9
ODCINEK 9
I need a little help.
Potrzebuję pomocy.
How much money you got?
Ile masz forsy?
Money? I don't have any. I used it all.
Forsy? Nic. Wszystko wydałem.
Liar.
Bzdura.
You're holding cash, right?
Musisz mieć gotówkę.
I failed as a conman.
Kiepski ze mnie oszust.
Serves you right!
Dobrze ci tak.
Seriously.
Poważnie.
-I've run out of options. -It's the same for me--
- Chwytam się brzytwy. - Ja też.
Hand over all of the cash you've got!
Oddawaj wszystko, co masz!
If you don't, I'll go get it from your house!
Inaczej przetrzepię ci chatę.
Go ahead.
Śmiało.
A piece of trash like you can't do anything on your own, anyway!
Taki śmieć i tak sam nic nie zdziała.
What did you say?
Że co?
Wait!
Czekaj!
I'll kill you!
Zatłukę cię!
Makoto!
Makoto!
Some of your friends broke into the house!
Twoi znajomi się tu włamali.
I know. I saw Misaki.
Wiem, widziałem Misaki.
-Misaki-chan... -What about the cops?
- Misaki... - A policja?
I didn't tell them anything.
Nic nie powiedziałam.
That's good. For now, just act normal.
I dobrze. Zachowuj się normalnie.
Normal?
Normalnie?
Yamada?
Yamada?
No, it's me! Get over to the office.
Nie, to ja. Do biura, już.
Dokugawa-san? But, I...
Pan Dokugawa? Ale...
Kanbe-san has talked to Tojo.
Kanbe i Tojo się dogadali.
Get your ass over here! Or else...
Rusz dupę, bo...
What is it?
Co się stało?
-I have to go. -Where?
- Muszę iść. - Dokąd?
I'll be right back!
Zaraz wracam.
Makoto! I got a call from the hospital!
Makoto! Dzwonili ze szpitala.
Your dad's coming home today...
Dziś wypuszczą tatę.
Hey, get to work!
Rusz się!
Damn...
Cholera.
Cover these in paint.
Zalej farbą.
Hurry up!
Ruchy!
Use the pole to mix it in.
Zamieszaj.
Like this, you idiot!
W ten sposób, durniu!
Thank you very much.
Dziękuję.
We did it!
Udało się!
Yes.
Tak.
We'll draw straws for how many pages.
Wylosujemy strony.
Why don't they try to share it with all of you who are suffering?
Czemu nie podzielą się z potrzebującymi?
That's why the elderly are a cancer on Japan.
Dlatego starsi ludzie to rak toczący Japonię.
If you hang on to this job, you'll never have to feel insecure
Jeśli wybierzecie tę pracę, zapomnicie o niepewności,
or unfulfilled or frustrated ever again.
braku spełnienia i frustracji.
You five have been chosen.
My wybraliśmy waszą piątkę.
THE ELDERLY ARE A CANCER ON JAPAN
STARSI LUDZIE TO RAK TOCZĄCY JAPONIĘ
Down with the elderly disease!
Staruchy do piachu!
-Down with the elderly disease! -Good!
Świetnie!
-Call the head office. -Yes, sir.
- Dzwoń do siedziby. - Tak jest.
Listen up.
Słuchajcie.
Even if you're caught, keep your mouths shut.
Jeśli was złapią, morda na kłódkę.
-Yes.
- Tak jest.
Good.
Doskonale.
And now your work is finished. Get out of here!
Zrobiliście swoje. Precz.
Dokugawa-san.
Panie Dokugawa.
Misaki...
Misaki...
I'm sorry.
Przepraszam.
What did the cops say?
Co mówiła policja?
Leave.
Odejdź.
-Please, don't say anything to-- -Leave!
- Nie mów nic... - Odejdź!
What are you doing?
Co ty wyprawiasz?
I told you, your dad gets home today.
Mówiłam, że tata dziś wraca.
I'm making a cake to celebrate.
Piekę ciasto.
A cake?
Ciasto?
This isn't the time for that.
To kiepski moment.
You told me, didn't you? I need to act normal.
Kazałeś mi zachowywać się normalnie.
Okay. I'll help.
Pomogę ci.
Let's start over again, as a family.
Zacznijmy od nowa. Jako rodzina.
From the beginning.
Od początku.
-Okay? -Okay.
- Dobrze? - Dobrze.
Let me.
Daj.
It's just like old times!
Jak kiedyś.
When you were little, you always made the frosting.
Jak byłeś mały, zawsze robiłeś lukier.
Do you remember?
Pamiętasz?
Yeah, I remember.
Tak.
Wait, no.
Czekaj.
What was it?
Co to było?
That half-baked dough inside the pancakes you made.
Wpółsurowe ciasto w naleśnikach.
That was my favorite.
Uwielbiałem je.
That's right.
To prawda.
I was always telling you you'd get sick if you ate too much.
Zawsze mówiłam, że się od niego pochorujesz.
Me and Misaki.
Misaki też.
She's been chiding me ever since we were kids.
Zawsze mnie rugała.
Misaki-chan...
Misaki...
I'm so sorry.
Tak mi przykro.
She was so scared.
Była przerażona.
Hey!
Ty!
You! Makoto!
Makoto!
Stop ignoring me!
Nie ignoruj mnie!
Does he ever shut up?
Czy on się zamknie?
This is all I have.
Więcej nie mam.
-This is it? -That's what I'm telling you!
- Tylko tyle? - Tak.
You're not hiding any, are you?
Nic nie ukrywasz?
I told you this is all I have!
Mówiłem, że to wszystko!
You're really pissing me off.
Wkurzasz mnie.
I'm busy, so get out of here!
Nie mam czasu, spadaj.
-What'd you say? -I said get out of here, asshole!
- Że co? - Wynocha, frajerze!
-I'll kill your mom! -Shut up!
- Zabiję twoją matkę! - Zamknij ryj.
-She said the baby was just born. -Is that so?
- Właśnie urodziła. - Tak?
I've caused a lot of trouble for you.
Narobiłem ci kłopotów.
It happens all the time.
Zawsze tak jest.
We'll take a little break and then get back into it.
Przeczekamy to i wrócimy do gry.
About that...
Właśnie.
-How do you feel about being the leader? -What?
- Nie chciałbyś poszefować? - Co?
Thank you so much!
Dziękuję!
Thank you.
Dziękuję.
Thank you very much, young man.
Bardzo dziękuję, młody człowieku.
Take care.
Proszę na siebie uważać.
You know, I'm tired.
Jestem wyczerpany.
All of the stores and people,
Chciałbym ci przekazać
I'm giving them to you.
wszystkie oddziały i personel.
Of course, I'll take care of everything with Tojo.
Porozmawiam z Tojem.
What do you think?
Co ty na to?
You're joking, right? Kanbe-san.
Chyba pan żartuje.
No.
Nie.
I'm serious.
Mówię poważnie.
But what will you do once you quit?
A co pan zrobi?
Move over to the financing side?
Zostanie pan inwestorem?
I don't think so.
Raczej nie.
I haven't really thought about it yet, but...
Jeszcze tego nie przemyślałem.
I think I'll try my hand at a normal job.
Chyba spróbuję legalnej pracy.
I wonder if...
Ciekawe...
it's possible to change after all this time.
czy jeszcze możemy się zmienić.
I'll try.
Spróbuję.
Wait, what's wrong?
Co się dzieje?
-Isn't it this? -Is it?
- To nie tym? - Może.
Okay.
No dobrze.
Are you okay?
Wszystko w porządku?
-Did you hurt yourself? -I'm fine, sorry.
- Nic ci nie jest? - Nie, wybacz.
-I'll get a towel. -Thanks.
- Pójdę po ścierkę. - Dziękuję.
Let's see.
No nie.
-Here. -Thank you.
- Proszę. - Dziękuję.
I'm sorry.
Przepraszam.
I'm going to quit.
Rzucam to.
I didn't know what to do.
Nie wiedziałem, co robić.
Dad got sick,
Tata zachorował,
and we had no money,
nie mieliśmy pieniędzy,
and I couldn't find a job.
nie mogłem znaleźć pracy.
The social welfare services did nothing to help us.
Pomoc społeczna nie kiwnęła palcem.
But I knew I needed to do something.
Ale musiałem coś wymyślić.
I didn't want to do anything bad.
Nie chciałem źle.
I just...
Tylko...
I didn't have a choice.
nie miałem wyboru.
I'm so sorry.
Przepraszam.
Makoto...
Makoto...
I don't think that's right.
Tak nie wolno.
It's your dad!
To tata!
Hello!
Cześć!
Welcome--
Witaj...
Is your son here?
Zastaliśmy pani syna?
-Find him. -Yes, sir!
- Znaleźć go. - Tak jest.
-You check over there. -Got it.
- Sprawdź tam. - Jasne.
I found him!
Mam go!
-Stop! -Hey!
- Stój! - Ej!
Stop!
Ani kroku!
-Come with us! -No!
- Idziesz z nami! - Nie!
Makoto Kusano.
Makoto Kusano.
You're under arrest.
Jesteś aresztowany.
Let go of me!
Puszczajcie!
Stop!
Nie!
Get up!
Wstawaj!
Let go of me!
Puśćcie mnie!
You didn't only take money from your victims...
Odebrałeś ofiarom nie tylko pieniądze,
you took their dignity!
ale i godność.
Shut up!
Nie mów tak!
You destroyed their dignity.
Odebrałeś im honor.
-Let go of me! -Do you know
- Puszczajcie! - Wiesz,
-how much they suffered? -Let go!
- ile wycierpieli? - Nie!
-Stop! -Depression.
- Dość! - Depresja.
Suicide.
Samobójstwa.
Did you think about that?
Przeszło ci to przez myśl?
-Shut up! -Your crime isn't scamming.
- Nie! - Nie tylko oszukiwałeś.
-Keep moving!
- Cicho! - Idziemy!
It's murder!
Ty mordowałeś.
-Let me go! -Makoto!
- Puśćcie mnie! - Makoto!
-Mom! -Get up!
- Mamo! - Wstawaj!
Makoto!
Makoto!
Stop fighting!
Nie rzucaj się!
-Mom! -Makoto!
- Mamo! - Makoto!
Come on!
Idziemy!
I did the best I could!
Starałem się!
I did everything I could!
Robiłem, co mogłem!
-Get up! -No one...
- Wstawaj! - Nikt...
Get up!
Góra!
No one was going to help us!
Nikt nie chciał nam pomóc!
Don't let him go!
Trzymajcie go!
What was I supposed to do?
Co miałem robić?
Hold on to him!
Trzymajcie!
Stop!
Nie!
-Kusano! -Stop!
- Kusano! - Nie!
Let go of me!
Puśćcie mnie!
-Makoto! -Let go!
- Makoto! - Puszczajcie!
-Quickly! -Makoto!
- Szybciej! - Makoto!
-Get in! -No!
- Wsiadaj! - Nie!
Makoto! Makoto!
Makoto!
Let me go!
Puśćcie mnie!
We won't just help you around the house.
Nie tylko pomożemy w domu.
If you join our A plan,
W przypadku wybrania planu A
in addition to daily safety checks,
zapewniamy codzienną kontrolę
we'll also provide support when you're hospitalized or move to a care facility,
oraz wsparcie w razie hospitalizacji lub pobytu w ośrodku opieki.
as well as for funeral and cremation services.
Pomagamy również w organizacji pogrzebu.
Okay.
Rozumiem.
Things sure are convenient nowadays.
Dziś to można żyć.
I don't have any family to care for me,
Nie mam krewnych,
so this would be a big help.
więc chętnie skorzystam.
Thank you.
Dziękuję.
It was a long time ago,
Wiele lat temu
but my son used to be a good swimmer.
mój syn był wspaniałym pływakiem.
Maybe some time, he could bring his friends from the team
Może kiedyś mógłby mnie odwiedzić
over to the house.
z kolegami z drużyny.
Yes, of course!
Oczywiście!
Our mission is to remove the anxiety
Pragniemy pokonać niepokój,
that comes from living alone so that you can enjoy your golden years.
który towarzyszy samotności. Dać panu radość na starość.
We're currently offering a discount that brings the total price down
Obecnie oferujemy zniżkę. Całkowita cena
from two million yen to only 1.8 million yen.
wynosi 1,8 miliona jenów zamiast dwóch.
Really?
Naprawdę?
It's a great discount.
To spora zniżka.
Thank you very much.
Bardzo dziękuję.
Thank you.
Dziękuję.
It's legal, I get to make old men and women happy,
Mam legalną pracę, uszczęśliwiam staruszków,
and I'm making money.
a do tego zarabiam.
What a great job.
Świetna robota.
No replies.
Zero odpowiedzi.
Kusano...
Kusano...
what are you doing?
Ciekawe, co u ciebie.
HEADQUARTERS FOR SPECIAL FRAUD
BIURO DS. OSZUSTW
CURRENTLY HIRING POLICE OFFICERS
ZATRUDNIMY FUNKCJONARIUSZY
Kusano, get up.
Wstawaj, Kusano.
If Misaki Azuma hadn't rescinded her testimony...
Gdyby Misaki Azuma nie wycofała zeznań...
I could have thrown you in prison.
trafiłbyś do paki.
Be ready.
Bądź na to gotów.
I won't let you get away next time.
Następnym razem się nie wymkniesz.
The world is cruel?
Świat jest okrutny?
No one will save us?
Nikt nas nie ocali?
I won't accept that!
Nie pozwolę na to!
Hey, Makoto.
Cześć, Makoto.
Long time no see.
Kopę lat.
Subtitle translation by Marti McElreath
Napisy: Konrad Szabowicz